Guide to the Carl V. Corley Papers, 1930s-2002 RL.00258
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl V. Corley papers
1930s-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Corley, Carl, 1921-2016
Allen, Sabina Allred, 1922-2008
RL.00258
21.75 Linear Feet 34 boxes
Carl V. Corley (1921-2016) was a white novelist and illustrator who served in the Marines during World War II. Collections contains the writings, drawings, scrapbooks, notebooks, correspondence, and published materials that document Corley's career and artistic output of Corley. The collection also includes typescripts and manuscripts of published and unpublished works of gay fiction, southern history, and heterosexual and homosexual erotica, some of which is in the form of comic books or graphic novels. The Sabina Allred Allen Collection of Carl Corley Papers includes correspondence and illustrations from Corley.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
Purchase and gift from Carl V. Corley in 1998. Accession 2017-0144 is a gift from Carl V. Corley via John Howard in 2017. Accession 2022-0017 is a gift received in 2022.
Biographical Note
Timeline
1921 Born in Florence, Mississippi
1939-1945 Served in the U.S. Marine Corps in the South Pacific
1947-1961 Illustrator, Staff Artist, and Unit Chief in the Mississippi Highway Department
1961-1981 Illustrator, Staff Artist, and Unit Chief in the Louisiana Highway Department
2016 Passed away in Jackson, Louisiana
Carl V. Corley was a white author and illustrator of a variety of materials such as gay pulp fiction, comic books, physique art, utopian science fiction, Louisiana history (especially on Cajun folkways), and also books on religious themes.
Corley was born in Florence, Mississippi in 1921. He graduated from Florence High School and served in the U.S. Marine Corps in the South Pacific in World War II. After the war, Corley worked as an illustrator for the Highway Department in Mississippi (1947-1961) and Louisiana (1961-1981). In his official capacities, he designed and drew tourist guides, manuals, pamphlets, road maps, and traffic surveys. In the 1970s and early 1980s, he contributed an illustrated strip on Louisiana folklore to the Eunice News. Corley passed away on November 3, 2016, in Jackson, Louisiana.
In the 1950s, Corley made a name for himself as a "physique artist," as he contributed drawings of scantily clad men to fitness magazines--a genre that has been identified by cultural historians as early homoerotica. Between 1966 and 1971, he published twenty-two paper back novels of gay male pulp fiction.
Sabina Allred Allen was born on June 21, 1922, to Robert and Mamie Allred in Mississippi. She married Bobby Arnold in September 1946, shortly after she and Corley ended their relationship. Sabina and Bobby divorced in May 1949, and then she married Dempsey Allen in June 1949. Sabina Allred Allen passed away on December 7, 2008, in Pearl, Mississippi.
Collection Overview
The Carl V. Corley papers contain the writings, drawings, scrapbooks, notebooks, and published materials that document the career and artistic output of the novelist and illustrator. The collection also includes typescripts and manuscripts of published and unpublished works of gay fiction, southern history, and heterosexual and homosexual erotica, some of which is in the form of comic books or graphic novels.
Corley's pulp novels were set primarily in early twentieth century Mississippi and Louisiana, though several were set in the South Pacific, where Corley served during World War II, and reflect varying degrees of autobiographical content. Corley's later works also show his interest in historical subject matter as well as utopian science fiction. Many of Corley's published and unpublished works include cover and textual illustrations produced by Corley.
The collection further includes photographs of the artist and friends, works by related authors and artists, correspondence with publishers, and some work-related notes and materials.
The Sabina Allred Allen Collection of Carl Corley papers consists of love letters written from Corley to Sabina during World War II, as well as artwork that Corley produced for Sabina during the war. Also extant is correspondence from Corley to Sabina dated 1999 through 2002, during which time Corley was working on an illustrated autobiography. Many of the letters from this later time period contain racist diatribes against Black Americans, as well as offensive language and stereotypes.
Separately Cataloged Material
A portion of printed materials written by Carl Carley and acquired with Acc. 1998-0087 have been separated from the manuscript collection and individually cataloged.
Works by Corley
A Gay Trilogy, 1967
A Lover Mourned, 1967
Attala Rose, 1968
Cast a Wistful Eye, 1968
Faces in Secret, 1967
In Homage to Priapus, 1970, edited by E.V.Griffith (includes an excerpt from A Fool's Advice by Carl Corley)
Jesse, Man of the Streets, 1968
My Purple Winter, 1966
Sky Eyes, 1967
Swamp Angel, 1971
That Gay Bar, 1968(?), no author listed
The Scarlet Lantern, 1966
Cajun Casanovas, 1988
The Rafe Saxon Mystery, 1989
"Today and Tomorrow: an engineering analysis of the highway transportation system in Mississippi," 1949
"Louisiana Boys and Girls State," 1968
The Purple Ring
Gay men -- Social life and customs -- Fiction; Homosexuality in art -- United States; Artists -- United States; Science fiction -- Illustrations; Authors, American -- 20th century; Illustrators -- United States; Authors and publishers -- United States -- Correspondence; Human figure in art; Louisiana -- History; Cajuns -- History; Cajuns -- Social life and customs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Ocean; Marines -- United States; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- Sexuality -- Fiction; Gay men -- Comicbooks, strips, etc.; Mississippi -- History; Scrapbooks; Typescripts; Photographs; Love letters; Corley, Carl, 1921-2016; United States. Marine Corps -- History -- World War, 1939-1945; Allen, Sabina Allred, 1922-2008
- Writings, 1955-1999 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Most of the works in this series are drafts and typescripts of novels by Corley, some including cover art or other illustrations. The Writings Series also includes clippings about Corley's work; correspondence between Corley, his editors and publishers; and personal corerspondence with family and friends.
  - A Rose for Caesar (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Bound typescript.
  - A New Earth (Box 1)
    Bound typescript re: Tiga Polo.
  - Tiga Polo Goes to Sola Roga (Box 1)
  - The Martyr Heart (Box 1)
  - The Black Ruby, 1955; 2 versions (Box 1)
  - Atomic Butterfly (Box 2)
    Typescript and some illustrations (using earlier title, Scarlet Lantern). Cover art included in Miscellaneous Illustrations.
  - Cad (Box 2)
    Typescript and cover art.
  - Goddess in Amber (Box 2)
    Typescript.
  - Ava (Box 2)
  - Soldiers in Silk: A Novel Based on Actual Experience, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Stardust (Box 2)
    Manuscript.
  - Afro Mania (Box 2)
    Manuscript, including cover art.
  - Goddess in Genesis, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Immortal Gods and Godless Mortals, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Star Over Eden, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Tara: A Sequel to Gone with the Wind, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - "Tara" Notes and research material, Undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
    Folders include handwritten notes on "Gone With the Wind" projected entitled "Tara", promotional material from the state of Georgia, city of Jonesboro, GA, a map of the state of Georgia, and storage folder.
  - Jaffe Ben Jorden: A Robot Who Played God, 4 folders (Box 3)
    Manuscript. Cover art included in file "Cover art for miscellaneous pulp novels."
  - Alexander, the True Messiah (Box 3)
  - After a God (Box 4)
    Bound typescript re: Roga St. Lo (alternate title Cotton Cavalier). Inside illustrations included in Illustrations and Comics Series.
  - Heart of Anger (Box 4)
  - El Sabine (Box 4)
    Typescript. Cover art included in file, "Cover art for miscellaneous pulp novels."
  - Jambalee, 3 Volumes (Box 4)
    Bound typescript. Cover art included in file, "Cover art for miscellaneous pulp novels."
  - Jambalee research notebook (Box 4)
  - Saddle Studs, 2 folders (Box 29)
    Typescript and file with research on cowboy lingo.
  - Rim of the World (Box 29)
    Typescript and cover art. Alternate title Prescience.
  - Sol Polo script, undated (Box 30)
    Script for illustrated science fiction saga entitled "Sol Polo" in a spiral notebook.
- Illustrations and Comics, 1950s-1990s; 2
  This series includes cover art, illustrated pages, and comics created by Corley throughout his career as a pulp novelist, newspaper cartoonist, and graphic novelist. Files are arranged by title, and include Corley's work with utopian science fiction, sexual fantasy novels, Louisiana and Southern history, and Biblical history. Also included are examples from Corley's work at the Louisiana and Mississippi Departments of Highways and his comics for a local newspaper, Louisiana's Eunice News.
  Corley's illustrations are largely pen or ink, drawn on paper or cardstock boards. Some titles include color, done by watercolor or tempra paint. There are also several titles, most notably the Louisiana history titles, which include collages or other paper media components. The majority of illustrations in this series are original artwork, but there are also several files with published newspaper clippings of Corley's work.
  Access Restrictions
  The Miscellaneous Illustrations and Comics file is closed to researchers because it contains Corley's social security number.
  - Miscellaneous illustrations, comics, and maps (Box 29)
    Includes a photograph of Corley.
  - Miscellaneous illustrations and comics (Box 29)
  - Autobiographical illustrations and comics, approximately 1970s-1980s (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Blaze Star: Stellar Conqueror of Exotic Females (Box 29)
    Illustrated pages and text.
  - Eunice News published cartoons (Box 29)
    Clippings from Eunice News of Corley's comics.
  - Fashion designs (Box 29)
    Illustrations by Corley for sex costumes.
  - Kix: Blazes New Trails for Sex (Box 6)
  - Fux, the Sex Fox (Box 6)
  - Rafe Saxon, Sex Warrior of Lust, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Sex Gods: An Exotic Pictorial (Box 7)
    Illustrated pages.
  - Illustrated History of Genesis, 4 folders (Box 8)
    Sample copy with illustrations and text, as well as 1 folder of disbound scrapbook pages with newspaper clippings of the comic.
  - Illustrated History of Genesis tear sheets, undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
    Tear sheets, text and images, from Corley's retelling of the biblical story of "Genesis" published in the Eunice, Louisiana newspaper every Sunday.
  - Scenes from Jesus's life, withdrawn from the Bible, 20 linolium tiles (Box 9)
    "Tempra paintings on tile depicting events that happened to Jesus Christ, but were withdrawn from the Holy Bible."
  - Pe'pa Paree in the History of Eunice, Louisiana (Box 5)
    Spiral-bound volume of newspaper clippings featuring Corley's comic strip about the history of Eunice.
  - Pe'pa Paree and the Story of Louisiana, 3 Volumes (Box 5)
    Spiral-bound volumes of newspaper clippings featuring Corley's history of Louisiana, part 1-3.
  - Pe'pa Paree and the Story of Louisiana, 2 Volumes (Box 6)
    Spiral-bound volumes of newspaper clippings featuring Corley's history of Louisiana, part 4-5.
  - Louisiana Festivals (Box 10)
    Illustrated pages and scrapbook of newspaper clippings with Corley's depictions of annual festivals throughout Louisiana.
  - In Louisiana: Plantation Life, Civil War, and Reconstruction, pages 1-36 (Box 11)
  - In Louisiana: Plantation Life, Civil War, and Reconstruction, pages 37-70 (Box 12)
  - History of Louisiana, pages 22-170, 1961 (Box 13)
    Illustrated pages and text, covering the birth of the landscape through the War of 1812.
  - History of Louisiana, pages 237-270, 1961 (Box 14)
    Illustrated pages and text, covering 1870-1888
  - History of Louisiana, pages 271-311, 1961 (Box 15)
    Illustrated pages and text, covering 1889-1929
  - History of Louisiana, pages 312-343, 1961 (Box 16)
    Illustrated pages and text, covering 1930-1961
  - Jafa Ben Jordan (Box 17)
  - Sola Flare (Box 17)
  - Roga (Box 18)
    Illustrated pages and text for 2 versions of Roga.
  - Jafa Jule (Box 19)
    Illustrated pages and text, incomplete.
  - Suny Blon (Box 20)
    Illustrated pages and text, Volume 3 and 5 (incomplete).
  - Papa Hi'Wae Sez... (Box 21)
    Comic strip panels with motivational or educational phrases, apparently intended for a the Dept. of Highways.
  - Alex Cale (Box 21)
    Corley's first comic strip. Bound volume with hand-colored illustrated pages and text.
  - Untitled comic strip [Floyd Ramond] (Box 21)
    Comic strip in bound scrapbook album.
  - Tiga Polo: Sex God of Stellar Space (Box 22)
  - 20 Miniatures of Louisiana Folk Art (Box 23)
    5x5 inch handpainted illustrations of Louisiana folk scenes.
  - Tee Don: The Littlest Journalist (Box 23)
    Alternative title: The Illustrated History of Arcadiana. Illustrated pages and text.
  - Sol Polo, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Blaze Exotica (Box 27)
  - Louisiana Area Maps/Historical posters (Box 27, Oversize-folder 1)
    Drawn by Corley for the Louisiana Dept. of Transportation and Development as part of his work for the Art and Models Unit. Includes regional maps as well as maps of historic homes, plantations, landmarks, and events in the state's history, including the Civil War and the Louisiana Purchase.
  - Mississippi Area Maps (Box 27)
    Drawn by Corley for the Mississippi State Highway Dept. Includes road maps.
  - Miscellaneous illustrations, including a self portrait. (Box 28)
  - Tony Polo, 1992 (Box 28)
    Illustrated pages, as submitted to Dark Horse Comics.
  - After a God (Box 28)
    Illustrated pages and cover art. Alternate title: Cotton Cavalier.
  - Pe'pa Paree miscellaneous illustrations (Box 28)
  - Cover art for miscellaneous pulp novels (Box 28, Oversize-folder 2)
    Titles include: Saddle Studs, Swamp Angel, Atomic Butterfly/Scarlet Lantern, Jambalee, Jesse, Satin Chaps, Attala Rose, El Sabine, Fallen Eagle, Purple Winter, Crescent Stud, Sky Eyes, Purple Ring, Walk the August Night, The Black Angel, Star Dusk, Jafa Ben Jordan, and A New Earth.
  - Pamphlets, 1960s-1970s; 2 (Box 30)
    Pamphlets featuring artwork by Corley, including one for a motel, a Baton Rouge tourist information pamphlet, and convention for state highway officials.
  - Illustrations, Undated; 2 (Box 30)
    Illustrations and photographic inspiration for Corley's artwork.
  - Cajun Casanovas, 1988; 2 (Box 30)
    Published erotic graphic novel entitled "Cajun Casanovas" including commentarty by Corley on its production.
  - Cover art from illustrated story of Joseph, Undated (Box 28)
    Cover art with annotation
  - Art collages and layout for Corley's autobiography (unpublished?), "Fire in the Cotton", approximately 1980s (Oversize-folder 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1930s-1990s; 3
  Scrapbooks include photographs, drawings, and notes relating to Corley's service in the Marine Corps in the Pacific during World War II. Scrapbooks also include research and preliminary studies for several books and comic strips. There are scrapbooks which document Corley's work for the Mississippi and Lousiana Departments of Highways. One scrapbook contains Corley's personal photographs of friends and lovers from high school to the present. Another scrapbook contains autobiographical material related to Corley's family and early life, as well as artistic inspiration and information about his career trajectory. Included are maps and posters relating to Mississippi and Lousiana history and geography created by Corley while working for the Department of Highways in both states.
  - Collection of newspaper clippings about Pe'pa Paree, 1969-1981; undated (Box 21)
    Bound scrapbook of newspaper clippings.
  - Mississippi State Highway Dept. portfolio ("No. 2") (Box 24)
  - Mississippi State Highway Dept. portfolio ("No. 3") (Box 24)
  - Photograph album of Corley's family, friends, lovers, and colleagues ("No. 4"), 1930s-1980s (Box 24)
  - Mississippi State Highway Dept. portfolio ("No. 5") (Box 24)
  - Scrapbook, 1950s-1980s (Box 25)
    Includes clippings, printed materials (cards, brochures, etc.) of Corley's artwork, and some correspondence.
  - Scrapbook album ("Photographs"), 1940s (Box 25)
    Includes some photographs from Corley's WWII service; clippings; sketches of Guam
  - World War II Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 26)
    Includes sketches, clippings, photographs, letters, poems, and other memorabilia from Corley's service in Guadacanal, Iwo Jima, and Guam.
  - Autobiographical Scrapbook, Undated; 3; 2 folders (Box 30)
    An autobiographical scrapbook, featuring photos and clippings pasted onto sheets of looseleaf paper. Scrapbook begins with Corley's family and traces his upbringing, his career, his artistic inspirations, and various examples of his work. Material also inclues photographs of friends and lovers.
  - Clippings re: Corley (Box 29)
- Correspondence, 1981-1999
  - Correspondence with editors and publishers, 1981-1997 (Box 29)
  - Personal correspondence, 1990-1999; 2 folders (Box 30)
    Personal correspondence with friends and relatives with some annotations by Corley regarding source and context for items.
- Sabina Allred Allen Collection of Carl Corley papers, 1942-1946; 1999-2002
  The Sabina Allred Allen Collection of Carl Corley papers consists of love letters written from Corley to Sabina during World War II, as well as artwork that Corley produced for Sabina during the war. The artwork accompanied Corley's letters but was separated from them prior to arriving at Duke. The letters frequently state how much Corley misses and loves Sabina, as well as their plans for engagement, marriage, and living together after the war. Many of the letters and envelopes were lightly annotated by Sabina, and some of the envelopes did not have any contents.
  This colelction also includes correspondence from Corley to Sabina dated 1999 through 2002, during which time Corley was working on an illustrated autobiography. It seems that Corley reconnected with Sabina because he needed her help reconstructing parts of his story. These letters contain requests for images and artwork, and they also discuss Corley's life, his dog, politics, diets, and the health of family members. Many of the letters from this later time period contain racist diatribes against Black Americans, as well as offensive language and stereotypes. Like the World War II-era material, these envelopes were annotated by Sabina.
  Also included in this collection is a small amount of correspondence from Corley to Sabina's parents, from Corley's mother to Sabina, and from Sabina to Corley.
  - Correspondence to Sabina Allred Allen, 1942 August - 1943 May; 7 folders (Box 31)
  - Correspondence to Sabina Allred Allen, 1943 June - 1946 September; 7 folders (Box 32)
  - Correspondence to Sabina Allred Allen, 1999 November - 2002 April; 5 folders (Box 33)
  - Correspondence to Sabina Allred Allen, circa 1942-1946; circa 1999-2002 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence from Sabina Allred Allen, circa 1942-1946; circa 1999-2002 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence to Sabina Allred Allen's parents, 1944; 1970s-1980s (Box 33)
  - Correspondence from Carl's mother to Sabina Allred Allen, 1943 (Box 33)
  - Artwork for Sabina Allred Allen, circa 1942-1946; 2 folders (Box 34)
    This artwork accompanied the letters that Carl Corley sent to Sabina during World War II. The artwork was separated from the letters prior to its arrival at Duke. Also present is a magazine cutout--the relationship of the cutout to the artwork (if any) is unclear.